<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An hue-and-cry after Vox Populi. Or, An answer to Vox Diaboli, or a libellous pamphlet falsly styled Vox Populi; reviling the magistracy and ministry of Norwich. Wherein is laid down, the truth of the rise and progresse of the said ministers of Norwich, their late remonstrance. Together with the deceitfull dealing of the Independent faction in getting hands to their petition there annexed, and their juggling in other petitions in that city. As also what entertainment their petition found in the Court of Majoralty and Committee for the County. Together with the entertainment of this scurrilous pamphlet in that city</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86691</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861672</idno>
  <idno type="VID">113813</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961071</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E355_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201111</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861672</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99861672e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E355[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An hue-and-cry after Vox Populi. Or, An answer to Vox Diaboli, or a libellous pamphlet falsly styled Vox Populi; reviling the magistracy and ministry of Norwich. Wherein is laid down, the truth of the rise and progresse of the said ministers of Norwich, their late remonstrance. Together with the deceitfull dealing of the Independent faction in getting hands to their petition there annexed, and their juggling in other petitions in that city. As also what entertainment their petition found in the Court of Majoralty and Committee for the County. Together with the entertainment of this scurrilous pamphlet in that city</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Martin, book-seller in Norwich, at the signe of the upper Halfe Moone in the Market-place,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Vox populi (Wing V730).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb: 25. London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Vox populi.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Norwich (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113813:1"/>
            <p>AN HVE-AND-CRY after <hi>VOX POPƲLI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, An Answer to <hi>ƲOX DIABOLI,</hi> or a Libellous Pamphlet falsly styled <hi>Ʋox Populi;</hi> reviling the Magistracy and Ministry of NORWICH.</p>
            <p>Wherein is laid downe, The truth of the Rise and Progresse of the said Ministers of <hi>Norwich,</hi> their late <hi>REMONSTRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the deceitfull dealing of the INDEPENDENT faction in getting hands to their Petition there annexed, and their jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in other Petitions in that City. As also what entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their Petition found in the Court of Majoralty and Committee for the County.</p>
            <p>Together with the entertainement of this Scurrilous Pamphlet in that City</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joh. 8.44.</hi>
                  </bibl> Ye are of your father the Devill, and the lusts of your father you will doe: He was a murtherer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth because there is no truth in him; when he speaketh a lye, he speaketh it of his owne, for hee is a lyer and the father of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pro. 12.19.</hi>
                  </bibl> A lying tongue is but for a moment.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pro. 10.8.</hi>
                  </bibl> A prating foole shall fall.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Edward Martin,</hi> Book-seller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> at the signe of the upper Halfe Moone in the Market-place. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113813:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113813:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Though I were neither a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, nor the Son of a Prophet, nor the friend of a Prophet; I could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to see so much dirt throwne in the face of all Authority, &amp; not pull out my handkerchife, though but to offer to wipe it off. These few lines in answer to this scurrilous Pamphlet, are onely to stay thy stomacke, till those Reverend men that are abused in it, have leasure to satisfie thee, themselves. This is onely an Hue-and-Cry to discover they will bring the Indictement against the Malefactor. I thought any cost was too much with this Haberdasher of small wares. Thou hast here the truth: though it be naked, couer it with Charity. I had no leasure to put it on, a gay coate of Rhethorick. 'Tis plaine, but there is no deceit in the webb. Lesse than this; my charity could not: More then this; my patience would not endure. Hee Barkt so loud, I could not but throw him a bone to gnaw: A Choak; till some discreeter hand bring him an Halter. Reader, I am an hater of lying and deceitfull lips, but a friend to thee, if thou beest a friend to Truth and Peace. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>1646.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113813:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113813:3"/>
            <head>An Hue and Cry after <hi>ƲOX POPVLI.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Praeface.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ʋr present division is a sad Omen: of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture miseries, and our happy unity would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly facilitate our desired felicity, would we all practise what we all professe, faith and love; we should all p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocure what we all desire, Truth and Peace: were wee all united in the Tri-une God; wee could not bee thus devided one from another.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis too known a policy (Sir) for you to deceive the world with, to cry whore, first. One would little think this mealy tongued Gentleman, were one of those Foxes that have fire-brands at their tailes, to burne what wheat God hath in this City. 'Tis very true (Sir) our present division is a sad <hi>Omen,</hi> of future miseries. But who are the <hi>Ominous</hi> birds? I could wish them cut off that trouble us, But I should be accounted two bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then: t'was <hi>Ahabs</hi> trick to meet <hi>Elijah,</hi> with a salutation most proper to himselfe; <hi>The Troubler of Israel.</hi> Our <hi>Ʋnion to God</hi> might keep us from this Division: and this makes us tremble to thinke of your seperation, <hi>Yee are gone out from us, if you had been of us, you had continued with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113813:4"/>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Difference of judgment, in the mystery of Divinity, is more our sorrow, then our sinne; because it is the irresistable product (through divine justice) of our depraved nature, inflicted upon us through anothers transgression, (the sinne of Adam) And is it in the power of meere men to bee all one in the vnity of the truth? But difference in Affection, anger, and choller, wrath, and hatred one to another, is more our sin then our sorrow, because against known, duty morall light, and naturall principles, and which of us doe improve his power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the same?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Ha! (Sir) who learned you this Divinity? was it one of your weekly Lectures? Are <hi>Misteria Theologiae,</hi> the deep fundamentall points, <hi>the mysteries of Divinitie</hi> so slightly in your esteeme? The Vnitie in them so little desirable amongst your tribe, that you thinke the difference here, (which must bee a difference from the truth too) is more our sorrow then our sin? Is it a sin to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the Truth, or no? especially (to use your owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression) <hi>In the mysteries of Divinity,</hi> yea or no? <hi>Paul</hi> would not have the <hi>Romanes</hi> ignorant in the miysteries. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11, 25. Is any sin more our sorrow then our sin? Let mee tell you what are these <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> these misteries: Faith is a mystery 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. <hi>The mystery of Faith.</hi> The Papists differ from us in the <hi>mysterie</hi> of Faith, and hold a destructive doctrine, Is this more their sorrow then their sin, think you? <hi>God manifest in the flesh,</hi> is a <hi>mystery</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 16. The Arrians differ from us in this <hi>mistery</hi> and deny such a deity. Is this more their sorrow then their sin, think you? Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, see what doctrine these brethren preach, are they not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee adored? why is it more our sorrow then our sin? The reason this learned Rabbi alledgeth seemeth to bee foure-fould, coucht in one sentence: if they lay uncoverd, every one would see their shame; wee will embare them a little.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is the unresistable product of our depraved nature,</hi> therefore it is more our sorrow then our sin. <hi>Mark</hi> (reader) the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans logick: whatsoever our corrupt Nature cannot but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, is more our sorrow then our sin:</p>
            <p>But our corupt nature cannot but produce a difference in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the <hi>mysteries</hi> of Divinity; <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very foule, make a Syllogisme and neither Proposition true: I see very little reason for the minor, for there is the same
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113813:4"/> principles of corruption in all. and how the same cause should produce contrary effects, I know not: I see no reason why it should bee the <hi>irresistable Product.</hi> But suppose it bee, for feare (by denying both) wee put the disputant out of breath; Is every <hi>unresistable product of our corrupt Nature more our sorrow then our sin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A naturall aversenesse from all good, &amp; pronesse to all evill <hi>is the irresistable pruduct of our depraved nature inflicted upon us for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers transgression</hi> and our owne too <hi>by the justice of God:</hi> and is this <hi>more our sorrow then our sin?</hi> (Sir) Doe you think the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> ever thought (when he found <hi>a law that when he would doe good, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill was present with him: when he saw another law in his members war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring against the law of his minde, and bringing him into captivitie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the law of sin which was in his members,</hi>) that this (which was an <hi>irresistable product of his corrupt Nature,</hi> or that remainder of corruption, left in him by divine justice,) <hi>was more his sorrow then his? sin</hi> what made him then cry out <hi>O wretched man that I am who shall deliver me from the body of Death?</hi> Rom. 7, 21, 22, 23, 24.</p>
            <p>The second, reason that this Gentleman would have us take, is, because it is inflicted <hi>through divine justice.</hi> The logick must be thus.</p>
            <p>Whatsoeuer divine justice inflicts uppon us is more our <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row then our sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this dissent in the <hi>mysteries of Divinitie</hi> is inflicted upon us by divine justice. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this fellow makes no better weight of plums, then he doth of his Arguments here; he deserves the pillony. An hard heart is often times an effect of divine Iustice: it was so in <hi>Pharaoh: Exod.</hi> 4, 21. was it more <hi>Pharaohs sorrow then his sin?</hi> Sodomy in the heathen, was the <hi>effect of divine justice,</hi> as well as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their sinfull Natures. Rom. 1, 24. <hi>Wherefore God gave them up &amp;c.</hi> was this <hi>more</hi> their <hi>sorrow then their sin? Sir?</hi> God often punisheth one sin with another: is that sin not a sin, because it is a punishment? Doth our <hi>Invincible</hi> ignorance, or wilfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse excuse us before God? will it excuse you (think you) at at the great day, to say, <hi>Lord, I could not but sin, Thy justice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted this upon one it was through thy justice, the irristable product of my Nature.</hi> If you have no better satisfaction, you will goe to the Devill. Take heed of hiding sin; or extenuating your sin, God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113813:5"/> will not be mocked, friend, you will one day finde that this sin which <hi>(through divine justice) hath been the irresistable product of your corrupt Nature,</hi> will be an everlasting Sorrow to you, except you confesse it something better, then here. How now (Sir) what all that sinke of sin, all the seed of Rebellion, that fountaine of filthinesse: that feeds our whole life with filthy streames, more <hi>Our sorrow then our sin?</hi> Is this so slight a sinne in an Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents Eye? Are you of the Popes minde, that thought the tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away of his Peacock was as great a cause of anger to him, as the taking of the forbidden fruit was to God? you will meet anon; well lets trace the Gentleman.</p>
            <p>His third reason seemes to bee couched in that sentence. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon us, through anothers transgression, the sin of Adam.</hi> This thing Independency is such a Chaos, I am forced to put all into forme for them: well, your Argument lies thus, in Logick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whatsoever is inflicted upon us through anothers transgression, the Sin of Adam is more our sorrow then our sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But this dissent in the mysterie of Divinitie is inflicted upon us through anothers transgression, the sin of Adam.</hi> And so all other branches of this tree of Originall corruption (for why this more then another) <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Make better waight Sir! Both propositions false, I should quarrell with the Gentleman; did I not know he were beyond his trade here, and, <hi>Nil sutor ultra crepidam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall pardon him for once, because I know his Occasions be more in his shop, then in his Study. Onely, let me a little <hi>answer a foole according to his folly, lest he bee wise in his owne conceit.</hi> Pro. 26, 5.</p>
            <p>Are you in earnest, Sir, when you hint to us that whatsoever is inflicted upon us for Adams transgression, <hi>is more our sorrow then our sin?</hi> all the filthinesse of our nature so slight, which no man can mourne enough for, suppose it bee not our sorrow at all; is it not our sin? Learne better Divinity, or for shame leave speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words of Exhortation. O, my soul pities those poore sovles that these seducers deceive.</p>
            <p>But to your minor, I deny that the dissent in judgment in the mysterie of divinity is inflicted upon us, for <hi>Adams</hi> transgression meerly, Which it must bee, or your tottering Argument will
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113813:5"/> bury it selfe in its owne ruines: Is their no inherent guilt in Originall sin? No doubt of your owne: All, your fathers left upon your score: Or supose it were: were it so slighty a matter as you think? Are you by nature children of whath, <hi>tam Acttivè quam Passivè</hi> and is this <hi>more your sorrow then your sin?</hi> Beleeve mee as slighty a thing as you make of; it If God should give you an acquittance, for all that ever you did from the begining of your life to this present hower, and to the day of your death; And it were not from the begining of the world, you should perish everlastingly.</p>
            <p>The last of his reasons seemeth to bee in those words: <hi>Is it in the power of meere men to bee all one in the vnity of the truth?</hi> The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument lies thus: <hi>If it bee not in the power of meere men to bee all one in the vnity of the truth; then difference in judgment in the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Divinitie, is more our sorrow then our sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it is not in the power of meere men to bee all one in the vnity of the truth. Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I must still call for weight, and deny the major: what though it be not in the power of meere men to be all one in the unity of the truth? is it not therefore a sin? or is not <hi>more their sorrow then their sin</hi> therefore? It is not in the power of meere man to be holy; is unholinesse therefore more their sorrow then their sin. It is not in the power of meere men to feare God, or walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in truth, and with a perfect heart; Is it no sin therefore or <hi>more their sorrow then their sin?</hi> Is nothing our sin but what we have power to do, or is it a slighty sin because we have not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? we have no power to fulfill the law of God. Rom. 7, 21. Acts. 13, 38. Acts. 15, 10. Rom. 8, 3. Gal. 3, 21. Rom. 8, 7. Man, as meere man hath no power: And because of this; wee have lost the power we had, Is it therefore no line? or is it so slighty a sin that it is <hi>more our sorrow then our sin?</hi> a poore slighty thing, do you think so? what think you of that dreadfull Commination. <hi>Cursed bee hee that continues not in all the things of the law to do them?</hi> are you of the Poets minde, Brethren, <hi>Vltra posse viri, non vult Deus ulla requiri?</hi> or of Plutarchs minde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is God tied up to such principles? are you of his minde that writ, <hi>Deus nec impossibile aliquid potuit imperare, quia justus est nec damnaturus est hominem pro eo quod non potuit vitare quòd pius est?</hi> What! are our Independents turned Pelagians or Manichees?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113813:6"/> Because it is not in our power to be one. <hi>Ergo.</hi> it is not our sin not to bee one in the <hi>mysteries of Divinitie,</hi> Or <hi>more our sorrow then our sinne:</hi> a poore slighty sinne, a veniall transgression. Take heed of Popery, Brother, what! have you slighty, and weighty sinnes? Hath not Christ commanded vnity, and commended it? doth this make it no sinne, to disobey and slight Gods commands and the Apostles precepts? <hi>Rom.</hi> 15, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 10. 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 27. 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4 <hi>Phil,</hi> 2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 2. Is it not an vnion in Opinion thinke you, as well as in Affection? But notwithstanding all this, the Independents think it a slighty sinne to dissent in judgment from others <hi>in the mysteries of Divinitie.</hi> because it is not <hi>in the power of meere man:</hi> (if any sinne at all.)</p>
            <p>But secondly: is it not in your power to labour for it? to come to Church? to heare those that would unblinde you; were you not willing to go blinde fold-to destruction? This is in your power: why is not this done? this would help you with an excuse some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better then your Argument.</p>
            <p>Well: this man goes on without the feare of God before his Eyes. <hi>But difference in Affection, anger and choler, wrath and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred one to another, is more our sinne then our sorrow, because against knowne duty, morall light and naturall principles: and which of us doe improve his power against the same?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doth this wretch beleeve that he that covereth his sinnes shall not prosper? Pro.</hi> 28, 13. A sinne against the first table immediatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, <hi>is more our sorrow then our sinne,</hi> a poore slighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But a sinne against the second table <hi>is more our sinne then our sorrow.</hi> An errour <hi>in the mysteries of divinitie,</hi> the secret fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall truths <hi>is more our sorow then our sinne:</hi> But a rash word in anger against our Brother, is more <hi>our sinne then our sorrow; with him.</hi> O, he ashamed if thou hast any thing of God in thee. Is not that the greatest sinne that is most immediatly reflexiue uppon God?</p>
            <p>Besides, is not that zeale which you call <hi>choler and anger?</hi> is it not a passion composed of loue as well as anger, love to Gods truth w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> you are corrupting: to his Church which you are ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: to the apple of his eye, which you are offending: to his deare people (committed to their charge) which you are seducing? is it a bitternesse against your persons? or against your doctrine and Iesuiticall practises? what presbyteriall Minister in Norwich
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113813:6"/> (Sir) ever preached against any of your persons? or writt? You have unchurched us: but if a minister be carefull over the sovles of his people, that you, under a deceit of holinesse entrap them not; Oh this is such choller (but it is pious (brethren) as cannot be endured. This is a sin farre beyond all heresy in the <hi>mysteries of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> or ignorance in the fundamentalls of christianitie, and <hi>and more our sinne then our sorrow,</hi> wee wish with you that <hi>every man even in his owne Spheare and according to his owne opportunity, would follow after the things that tend unto peace: So our common pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity soone would be effected.</hi> But doth this <hi>Vox Diaboli tend to peace? this slanderous pamphlet? did you move in your owne Spheare here?</hi> It was never weighed in the Ballance of truth. I will assure you It is a false <hi>weight and a deceitfull Ballance, &amp;c.</hi> but for this, if the Independents will goe about to <hi>shew us any good</hi> I am deceived in their designes <hi>For loe, (say you) those whose very office, and function is the propagation of peace, improve their indeavours to the promotion of troubles, And our Peace-Preachers turn our Bate-makers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very true, (Sir) if you speake of your selves: Witnesse, your pastors gathering of Churches, dividing in Families, carrying away wife from husband, one friend from other: witnesse the preaching and praying, and printing of your Tribe, against our brethren of Scotland. Though (the Lord be praised,) <hi>he hath made you lyers unto him,</hi> and their innocency <hi>cleare as the Sunn in his fight:</hi> Witnesse, your frequent lies, and slanders, of that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nation, which fill'd every pamphlet: Witnesse, your draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peoples affection from their ministers &amp;c. Never such Bate-makers, If I have not lost my judgement. The Lord judge betwixt us, and you for that. For your insuing story.</p>
            <p>I shall examine that, &amp; see if you have better Principles of Truth then you have had any of reason in you in your preface. The first part of his story is concerning some passages of a Sermon preacht <hi>Iune</hi> 16. being the Guild day. here he describes the place and auditory. <hi>(the whole City generally attending)</hi> (where note, the greater part of that City are no Independents, as some of the tribe boasts) But to the purpose: the charge is, That in that Sermon the said Master <hi>Thornebeck did exhort the people to strike in</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">with some petition, that some course might bee taken, to tread out those sparkes that were ready to set on fire both Kingdomes: and if any wretch should interpose, or go about to hinder it; Hee deserves to bee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113813:7"/> cut in pieces and his house to bee made a jaques.</q> First I answer, that it is false: <hi>(quo ad formam)</hi> he spake of no petition; only moved them to sett up reformation and further that, desiring to improve that houre to put on authority to act for God according to their severall places; and is this his charge? he might exhort them to <hi>tread out those sparkes which are ready to set on fire both Kingdomes,</hi> and was it not according to his Covenant? have wee not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged our selues to God <hi>To discover Incendiaries,</hi> and labour to <hi>bring those to condigne punishment?</hi> And are not these <hi>Incendiaries</hi> in the Covenant-sence, <hi>that labour to divide betwixt the King and his people,</hi> or, <hi>betwixt the two Nations of England and Scotland?</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he had named <hi>Independents,</hi> I know no crime in it; what hath meant their long acted designe to bring the <hi>Scotts</hi> &amp; <hi>English</hi> into jealousies one of another? was not <hi>The Black cloud in the North</hi> of that tribes raising? What have ment their Virulent tongues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them and their poisoned pens? and the many lyes, that the world hath been filled with (touching that true-hearted Nation) how have their <hi>Simeons and Levies</hi> indeavoured to make the name of <hi>Iacob</hi> stinke amongst the inhabitants of our <hi>Land?</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he had exhorted them in direct termes, to strike in with a petition against the Faction of Independancy, the greatest fire that now consumes our kingdome if under that Notion. And that be true: who so would hinder it, deserves to have no name in Israel. Thus much for the clearing of the text, Now to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amaine the Commentary a little.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">First by the way, This sectary takes notice hence of the prime fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters, and chief Authors of this kinde of States-disturbing practice, of Cities and countries, <hi>viz.</hi> those that speake unto the people in the name of Lord, who have greatest force, power, &amp; interest in the hearts, a people who look upon them as their Seers, their Guids, men acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the will of God</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Men not steered by carnall interests, but as aming simply at the glory of God, and wel-fare of their soules, who watch for their good, and therfore (in the simplicity of their harts knowing nothing,) they are ready to Act according to their own hearts device; for the truth is, conscience is a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thing, and if once mens judgments are misinformed and abused by their ministers, and prophets; if they say, and that in the name of the Lord, Go up to Ramoth Gilead and prosper thousands will bee ready to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113813:7"/> march though to their own ruine.</hi> A pretty note this! tis pity the Margent had not a hand to point out the Knave.</p>
            <p>The complaint is of a State disturbed: there note
<list>
                  <item>1. The manner of the disturbance.
<list>
                        <item>1. By preaching faithfully and zealously for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</item>
                        <item>2. By petitioning Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity humbly.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The Disturbers of it.
<list>
                        <item>1. Those that speak unto the people in the name of the Lord.</item>
                        <item>2. Those that have greatest interest in the peoples hearts.</item>
                        <item>3. Those that are lookt upon as the peoples guides, &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The people disturbed: in which
<list>
                        <item>1. Their quality.
<list>
                              <item>Those that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire Ministers to acquaint them the will of God</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. Their readinesse to be disturbed.
<list>
                              <item>Ready to act according to their hearts desire, &amp;c.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Is preaching for a Reformation faithfully and zealously, the disturbance of a State, is this such a disturbing practice? <hi>O tempora! O mores!— Quis sit inquae Tam patiens Gentis? tam fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus ut teneat se?</hi> This was the Bishops language: are you turned faces about? Is discharging our conscience faithfully, (which is the blessing of a State) the disturbing of a State? Reader, note, that faithfull preaching is the Independents disturbance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is humble Petitioning the disturbing practise? did you thinke our petitioning against the Booke of <hi>Common-prayer</hi> and <hi>Bishops,</hi> so? Is, to <hi>speake in the name of the Lord to a people</hi> to disturbe that people, or the presenting our groanings to the Parliament, such a disturbance? The Lord awaken you, and trouble you thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113813:8"/> while your troubled waters be still. But who are they that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb the state?</p>
            <p>Surely, they are such as seduce the King, or blow up the coales betwixt brethren, or gather Churches out of Churches. These, a man in his wits, and would judg those that trouble Israel: those that hinder proceedings in the Assemblie, or in the Courts of Justice. Thus a wise man would think. But what sayes our <hi>Abab? Elijah is the man that troubles Israel.</hi> Shall I give you a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of them out of his own shamelesse mouth?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>They are such as speake to the people in the name of the Lord.</hi> O were not there a godly Preacher a Presbyterian, to convert souls. But we were all Heathens, then this Sectary would bee quiet: 'tis this indeed that troubles their
<list>
                  <item>Gathering</item>
                  <item>Scattering</item>
               </list> of Churches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They are such as have greatest force, power, and interest in peoples hearts,</hi> such as have converted the peoples soules to God, and so ingratiated themselves to the people, and are written in their soules. These are those that troubled the Bishops, and now, the Independents: these are those that will not subscribe their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and disswade their people from their practices. For shame (Sir) blush: are these those that trouble the State?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>They are such as the people looke upon as their seers and guides, men acquainted with the will of God, men not steered by carnall inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests, but as ayming simply at the good of their soules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are these your enemies? those that are acquainted with the will of God, whom you professe alliance to? those who purely looke at the salvation of soules (if all mens eyes be not blinded, beside the Independents, those that <hi>watch for your good.</hi> Now I hope the world will take notice what a Sonne of <hi>Belial</hi> this is, who accounts the unbiast faithfull Seer, <hi>the author and fomenter of these State-disturbing practises.</hi> But in the third place are who, these that are thus disturbed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take notice of their quality. They are those that look after unbiast Ministers, that are acquainted with the wil of God, those that have a desire to the Word: that in this Schismaticks mouth <hi>(in the simplicity of their hearts know nothing:)</hi> surely these <hi>are preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous stones: if they were but cemented in your Church,</hi> they would know something. Are these the Major and Court of Aldermen, and Common Councell, and Commonalty of this famous City,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113813:8"/> such poore simple creatures, <hi>that they know nothing:</hi> (yes Sir, they know you for a seducer) and with a twine thrid they may bee drawn to act what their Ministers would have them, good or bad, swallowing all. Yea if they say, <hi>Goe up to</hi> Ramoth Gilead, <hi>and prosper, these thousands will march though it be to their ruine:</hi> Sure, this famous Citie will take notice of this Abuse. But surely your Independent Ministers have not had so good fortune here to lead them. Neither Major nor one Alderman member yet: your two Lectures and constant Sabboth Sermons, and double weekely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, and publike insinuations, and private tricks, have not found <hi>Norwich</hi> such a lob-cocke Citie as you would have it: Are only the thirty men and fourscore women, of your Church, and the best of them scarce a Common-councell man, with the rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of poore mechanicks &amp; silly women, entrap'd in your snare, the only men in <hi>Norwich,</hi> that will examine the Scriptures for <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine?</p>
            <p>The second note the Gentlemen observes, is <hi>The meanes, wayes and methods that they put the people upon for the bringing about their designe, that is by Petitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Those in the Kings quarters did exhort the people with a ful mouth to take up arms for his Majestie the Lords Annointed, promising ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and assistance in the Name of the Lord. But those in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments quarters to Petition again and againe, to shoot arrow after arrow, and promiseth upon this course (if continued) that they shall succeed and prosper: for what may they not doe? if they will shew themselves not to give over Petitioning till they have their desires, &amp; if one failes, give not over, strike higher yet, be positive in your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but be sure you have soft Epithites to your titles: let it bee the humble Petition and humble Remonstrance, and dash it here &amp; there with a few good words, acknowledging what the Parliament hath done, with all humility and thankefulnesse, and let your Prayer be something to that purpose: for, what ever it is, if the number of the hands, and the quality of the subscribers declare them many, great, and strong, and the phrases of their Petitions, the resolutions of their spirits; the Parliament must yeeld.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here observe what angers the Gentleman: O this petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning! this makes them all lyars, who would boast of so many they have of their side, the greater part of the Citie of <hi>Norwich,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113813:9"/> the Aldermen and Common-councell, the Knights, Gentlemen, and Free-holders of the County of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and County &amp; Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Norwich,</hi> page 16. when scarce a Knight or a Gentlemans hand to it, (but, of that, and the brave jugling for it, more anon.) All these tricks Petitioning spoiles. But Sir, is not Petitioning, the Subjects priviledge in <hi>England?</hi> is it not their birth-right? for those words again, <hi>shoot arrow after arrow, and promiseth upon this course if continued, they shall prosper, &amp;c.</hi> This piece of impudence would make us beleeve by this continued lying dialect were a piece of Mr. <hi>Thornbecks</hi> Sermon, but Sir that is false every sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And for the <hi>soft Epithites and humble Remonstrance, &amp;c.</hi> it is your own dialect, <hi>page</hi> 16. But the most of your Tribe will not give them so much as good words: doe you remember your saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy brother Mar-priest and <hi>Lilbourn,</hi> and those that have defended them: were ever the Peers of <hi>England</hi> so abused by a faction? Neither is it our intention to make the Parliament yield, but by petition to present our grievances. Let the world judge, have you had such raw-mannered Presbyterians as Independents? marke their preaching and printing, which gives the Parliament most honour? But I shall shame you anon, with your getting hands to your Petition; I could tell you, of their hands that cannot distinguish betwixt their right hand and left: but of this in its due place.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Thirdly, he tells us we may consider the matter of those Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Remonstrances, which are most disturbing the Church and State. And that is the suppression of that sort of people, though never so holy, harmlesse, peaceable, usefull to the publique good. If so be they observe them destructive unto their designes, and hinderers of their hopes, and selfe-exalting endeavours. Drunkards, Swearers, Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Lyars, Whoremongers, Adulterers, &amp;c. are not Petitioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against, because these do not hinder them in their wayes; but whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver those be that differ from them in judgement, and oppose them in their way, these are Heretickes, Sectaries, Schismaticks, and what not?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here's three or four falshoods insinuated.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the people that are petitioned against, are <hi>holy, harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, peaceable, usefull to the publique good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Ministers only petition against these, <hi>because they are obstructive to their designes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113813:9"/>3. That they are favourers of <hi>Drunkards and Swearers, &amp;c.</hi> they are not Petitioned against.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That their greatest crime is a little <hi>difference in judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the first: your holinesse: I thinke you have no more then you need: holy <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and <hi>Antinomians,</hi> many of you: for your holinesse; more anon: but are you so harmlesse and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble too, abusing Magistrates, reviling Ministers? against whom you have nothing to say. But they are no <hi>Independents.</hi> I shall tell you of some of your harmlesse doings, and peaceable trickes anon, you are not such tame fooles as you would make your selves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is the Ministers only quarrell against you (thinke you) because you are <hi>obstructive to their designes,</hi> and hinderers of their hopes? No (Sir) it is because you corrupt their Congregations, seduce their people, deceive silly soules: this is the quarrell, wee can leave it to God to work out our designes, and throw these chipps out of the way. And we feare not but the Meteor wil va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish alone: The <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> will goe out of it self: the Mushroom of Indepedency is but for a day or two: The Babell will down againe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Are these such favourers of <hi>Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, Gamesters, Whoremongers, Adulterers,</hi> as your sawcy pen would whisper them to be? One thing is, their integrity is of a little longer date then yours (good Brother!) your tongue is no great slander. But <hi>these are not Petitioned against;</hi> We will tell you the Reason. First, for Drunkards, Swearers, Adulterers, Gamesters, there is direct statutes against them, and we know the Majors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity to be such, that if you but goe and convict any of your members before him; he will execute them to the utmost as upon any others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For Lyers: we confesse we have no direct statute against: and therefore wee petitioned against them <hi>inclusivé</hi> inclusively, when wee petitioned against you: (onely in more mannerly termes) and I hope to correct you anon: and if I thought you would not confesse them: I would tally them for you, or set an hand against them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is the greatest crime you are guilty of, <hi>difference in judgment?</hi> No (Sir), we are not angry with you for this, it is your distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113813:10"/> practise! It is, your gathering of Churches, drawing wift from husband, and children from Parents: It is, the complain that wives take from their husbands, to maintain your Pastors: Is this the <hi>difference in judgement?</hi> (speake truth Sir) I shall tally presently.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>But come we to his last note. Fourthly, he will consider</hi> the Notion under which they represent their dissenting Brethren, <hi>viz.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries, sparkes that are ready to set on fire two Kingdoms, when alas they are meerly passive &amp; act nothing, but desire to be let alone, &amp; themselves doe little lesse then throw balls of Wilde-fire from their Pulpits and pens, setting on fire the whole Kingdome: and the trueth is, this Generation of men hath almost involved that part of the world that is called Christian, in most fiery and bloody contestations: and if all things be rightly considered, as we very well know, and may see whence our late warres did proceed, <hi>viz.</hi> from the Prelates, some of them not being ashamed to call it <hi>Bellum Episcopale:</hi> so we cannot but take notice who it is that is fomenting new differences and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies betweene Parliament and People, dividing a most prosperous and united party, one against another, insinuating it is very much fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into a new war, which can properly be nothing else then <hi>Bellum Presbyteriale,</hi> as will further appeare by the rest of this story concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Norwich</hi> Remonstrance, which followes, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In this Copious lye take notice of two things:
<list>
                  <item>1. An Excusation
<list>
                        <item>The parties excused
<list>
                              <item>Dissenting brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren represented as Incendiaries.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>The excusation it self.
<list>
                              <item>They are meerely passive and act no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp;c.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. An Accusation:
<list>
                        <item>The parties accused:
<list>
                              <item>They; that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the will of God, &amp;c. <hi>ut prius.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Comparison: To Prelates and their practises.</item>
                        <item>The positive Accusation
<list>
                              <item>Sedition, &amp;c.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113813:10"/>
            <p>I shall spend a few lines to accuse the Excused, and excuse the Accused. least <hi>I justify the Generation of the wicked, and condemne the Generation of the just, Both which are abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parties Excused are represented under a double Notion: First in their neighbours glasse: So they are <hi>Incendiaries dividing betwixt wife and husband, Minister</hi> and <hi>People, England and Scotland:</hi> And are only petitiond against under this Notion: (in their own confession) if they plead not Guilty, and can cleare themselves. there is no more desired, Or if they will traverse the Inditement and be tried by their Peers, they may: Is this such a State-disturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing practice? (Brother) Is it not a Covenant-clause. Who will you be tried by?</p>
            <p n="2">2. In their own Glasse: and heere the Aethiopians are fair, alas! what have they done? <hi>they are meerly passive</hi> and <hi>act nothing but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to bee let alone,</hi> poore tame creatures! they have a faire tongue but this is a foule falshood do you act nothing in the Assembly? Nothing in the Parliament? Nothing in the Armie? Nothing in London? Nothing in the Presse? Nothing in Norwich? how come the Faction so spread, that the locusts cover the land? how came so many Churches gathered? They act nothing, when in any election, besides their privat tricks, and insinuations, they will use any indirect meanes for their side to carry it, give pottles of Sack almost to drunkennesse: give their voyce rather for the greatest Malignant, or profane person; that they think will bee for a Cypher, then for a godly man if a Presbyterian: they act nothing when if one bee chosen, that is (as they think) one that desires peace in the state and vnity in the Church) they (though against their own consciences.) will bee petitioning against him for a Malignant. hoping by this meanes, if they cannot turn him out: yet they will raise an ill report of him, that he might not bee accounted of. These acted nothing against Sir Iohn Hobarts Election: when they would have made him a Malignant, though he hath been more faithfull, and done the Parliament more ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice then their whole tribe in the County. The world under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands your dealings, wee could tell you of damnable acting. <hi>Machiavell</hi> never acted so much: yet they are tame creatures, if they might bee beleeved; and <hi>desire to bee let alone.</hi> Cut a mans throat and then a fling away the knife, and ask who meddles
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113813:11"/> with him? they <hi>desire to bee let alone,</hi> So did the <hi>Arminians,</hi> And no question, the most prodigious Traytors, when they came to bee discovered, would have been let alone too: you are <hi>meerly passive.</hi> why? what have you suffred I pray? what, have you been exiles? who hath been so passive? your brother <hi>Lilbourne</hi> hath suffered Imprisonment, when he deserved the worst of Deathes. But so much for your excusations: A little to vindicate the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who are accused? [They.] viz. <hi>that speake to the people in the name of the Lord, that have greatest force and power, and interest in the peoples hearts:</hi> these are the accused. you may guesse by the rule of the Contraries, who are the Accusers: those that look upon these as the State-disturbers, Surely we have done something for God more then wee thought of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mark the comparison: Betwixt the Prelats and us: what! have you none to compare them with, but those that suspended and excommunicated, and hunted after them? were these Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in <hi>Bello episcopali,</hi> or combatants against it? But impudencie hath no fore-head. I shall, vindicate them from this in the due place: where this brazen-faced Sectary speaks more home and full. Let us examine the Accusation it self.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sedition: <hi>throwing Balles of wildfire</hi> and <hi>setting on fire the whole Kingdom, involving the greatest part of the Christian world in most fiery and bloody contestations,</hi> Harsh language! did not the Authors credit flag, it might make the people pull the Ministers out of the Pulpits: but doth the <hi>accquaintance</hi> they have <hi>with the will of God</hi> teach them such things? So all the Prophets, and Apostles preacht sedition. <hi>Paul</hi> preacht absolute Sedition at <hi>Ephesus.</hi> But guesse (Reader) (when the Silversmiths cry, and other Crafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of the like occupation) the reason, <hi>Acts.</hi> 19, 25. <hi>Sirs By this Craft they have their wealth. Moreover they see and heare, that not only at</hi> Norwich, but almost <hi>throughout all the Kingdome,</hi> these Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters <hi>have perswaded, and turned much people</hi> to God, <hi>and</hi> his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>Saying that this</hi> Independency is a meere Anarchy; a thing made with hands. <hi>So that not only this their craft, is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to bee sett at nought; but also that the Temple of the great</hi> Diana of Independency <hi>will be dispised,</hi> and their magnificence <hi>shall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed,</hi> this makes them <hi>full of wrath</hi> to cry out: But <hi>Brother De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius!
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113813:11"/> and the craftsmen of your society; if you have any matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any of these men, the law is open: and there are deputies; let them implead one another.</hi> In the meane while, let not your tongue bely your conscience: nor yet out-run your witt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The second is <hi>dissimulation,</hi> this they are charged with: that they are the first that cry <hi>fire, fire,</hi> when they, sais hee: are the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is a Libell (good Sir) and if your book hath not the better license, you may hap to hear of this at the pillory. I shall leave the law to answer this at the Courts discretion, get <hi>Iohn Batchilers</hi> hand to it: Quickly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is Suspition of a <hi>Bellum Presbyteriale.</hi> Alas the day, This will not doe. If the <hi>Scots</hi> and we should quarrell, (which the Lord in mercy prevent, and shame those that make it their designe to bring about) all the world knows the cause, we shall goe nigh to Chronicle it <hi>Bellum Independens:</hi> we have heard some of your Sermons, and read some of your bookes, and observe your tricks to beget jealousies betwixt the <hi>Scots,</hi> by raising the lies of <hi>ten thousand Scots newly come in,</hi> and <hi>Barwicke and Tinmouth fortified:</hi> and ten thousand devices more, which the Lord hath discovered and confounded, (Praised be his Name!)</p>
            <p>But to proceed, page 4.</p>
            <p>It is confest: p. 4. thus far, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Ministers there na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med did <hi>goe to the Court of Aldermen, and desired the Major that an Assembly might be called the next day, and then they would tender un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a Petition or Remonstrance to the Parliament, &amp;c. And it is true, the Court desired to see their Petition, &amp;c. which they promised they should see at the said common Assembly: In conclusion they did yield it should be read by one of themselves: but not by the Town-Clarke, &amp;c.</hi> The Text is corrupted, but we shall finde the Commentary abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and have liberty there to meet with it.</p>
            <p>First saies he, <hi>we further see whence these kinde of Remonstrances have their rise and spring,</hi> viz. <hi>from the Ministers in the Countrey, they beare sway and command, and appeare publique in their designes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how do you see here further? (good Logicall Sir.) Marke your Argument. If the Ministers of <hi>Norwich</hi> bee the Authors of this Remonstrance, then the Ministers in the Countrey are the Authors of those Remonstrances are sent out of the Countrey.</p>
            <p>But these. &amp;c. —<hi>Ergo</hi> those.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113813:12"/>
            <p>I must still tell you of a false weight, your ballance of reason is nought, Sir, and the weights of your braines want the seale of judgment. Give me leave to turne it into your bosome.</p>
            <p>If the female Independents in London steale from their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to enrich their Pastors; then they do so in <hi>Norwich,</hi> the Countrey and other places (look about you Gentlemen!) But &amp;c. —<hi>Ergo:</hi> is this good Logicke?</p>
            <p>If the Independents in <hi>London</hi> admit all riff raff of <hi>Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Antinomians</hi> into their Church, provided they keep their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions to themselves: then they doe so in <hi>Norwich,</hi> and other places. But &amp;c. —<hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I shall anger you anon with disputing in your own mood and figure. Learn better logick, reasonable men will be ashamed to meddle with you.</p>
            <p>The Ministers <hi>beare sway and command.</hi> No (Sir) they onely Remonstrate, exhort, petition, entreat. But <hi>they appeare publique in their designes.</hi> The more their credit, they act above-board: if you had done so, you had wanted hands to your Petition. It is an argument, they are not ashamed of their actions: It is an argument their designes are good and commendable, such as they dare appeare in publike unto.</p>
            <p>But secondly, he notes <hi>the policie of these Ministers f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all carrying on their works:</hi> (The wisedome of Serpents, Sir.) <hi>First they publiquely prepare the people by their Sermons.</hi> 'Tis for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (Sir) oh that we were better prepared for it: <hi>after that, they privately addresse themselves to the Magistrates.</hi> 'Tis false Sir, this was publikely too at the open Court.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Master</hi> Thornbeck <hi>he sais took advantage</hi> (to discharge his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science) <hi>from that extraordinary convention of the whole collective City at Sermon, To prepare their judgements:</hi> Another abuse put upon the whole Citie. First, that all of them should be of such weake unsetled judgements, that the Minister must prepare them, as if this whole Citie were a nose of waxe to be turned by the voyce of the Minister. But know, Sir, Their judgement was already Presbyterian: which of them is a member in your Church? It is well you can speake any thing true: it was indeed <hi>to stir up their affection:</hi> all of us had need have our affections quickned to the good worke of Reformation, to act it in our severall places. For
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113813:12"/>
               <hi>the promotion of the remonstrance,</hi> no such was exprest; I dare not search their hearts, nor their thoughts; who gave you commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to doe it? still he goes on for the whetstone.<note place="margin">☜</note>
               <hi>In the afternoon it was seconded by</hi> Master <hi>Bond, violently pressing the people; according to the pattern delivered him in the mount, I meane</hi> Master <hi>Thornbecks Sermon.</hi> First, (Sir) Master <hi>Bond;</hi> in stead of violent pressing, spake not a word of it, but suppose he had; if Master <hi>Thornbecks</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon were <hi>as the pattern in the mount,</hi> Gods word and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God; what harme heere?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next day after he saith striking (while the Iron was hot) they applyed themselves to the Magistrates:</hi> they did not do any thing of themselves, then, but with the Advice of the Magistrates. He saith, <hi>This hath been alwayes observed; that the magistrates must doe the Ministers work.</hi> No Presbyteriā Magistrates, (Sir) they are your Magistrates that do the Ministers work: <hi>viz.</hi> preaching and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, wee give no such libery: It is the worke of God, ours doe: to which wee exhort them, and intreat them.</p>
            <p>He goes on in his tedious folly. I should trouble the Readers patience, and mine own too, to read or write them: One thing I must take notice of. <hi>He talks of Invectives they beare in the Ministers pulpits, complaints in their prayers against the evill of the times</hi> (that is their duty) <hi>that there is no reformation,</hi> that is the groaning of their sadded sovles: <hi>No vniformity: Gods house lies wast: all runs to confusion.</hi> Too just complaints! Oh that they were not put into their mouthes! <hi>Sects, Sectaries, Hereticks, Schismaticks grow and multiply:</hi> The Lord root them out; Now this reverend crafts-man will expound their meaning. <hi>But what is this reformation: but the establishing of Power, Authority, and Estate, in the hands of the clergy.</hi> What power is desired, or Authority? but what the word of God allowes: I am confident they could hartily wish it allowed them none at all, Our greatest care is, least any secular authority should offend our God, by taking more into their hands then Gods word allowes; not for feare wee should not have enough: <hi>let them take all,</hi> (if Gods word will allow it) so our Church be settled in peace: but hee talks of <hi>Settling estate in the hand of the Clergy;</hi> which of the Presbyterians estate is it you envy? Alas! that one president of <hi>good Docter Burges</hi> doth so stick in your throat; you forget, 200 <hi>pounds per annum,</hi> given to your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113813:13"/>
               <hi>Peters:</hi> 300. <hi>per annum:</hi> that another hath. And, Is that the reformation you desire, to have them have a Church at <hi>London,</hi> &amp; one or two more in <hi>Norfolk</hi> &amp; <hi>Norwich?</hi> truly your Clergy for the present want no great— how can they when Master <hi>H. K.</hi> a man of no great fortunes, gives eighteene pounds <hi>per annum:</hi> and Master <hi>I. T.</hi> in <hi>Norwich</hi> too, gives eight pound <hi>per annum?</hi> you have not such a cheap clergy when men of these estates are faint to straine so hard: <hi>we heare nothing</hi> saith hee <hi>almost in every Pulpit but Church discipline, vniformity: Nothing against the known, God-provoking sins of the time;</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>
               <hi>Swearing, lying, defrauding, cousening, and over-reaching one another: little or nothing of the doctrine of Faith to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, repentance from dead works, love amongst Brethren, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, Vnion with Christ, fellowship with the Spirit; these things are almost bannished the Pulpits, and wee have nothing but the very formes and shell of Religion preached in the roome thereof.</hi> Wee which of the wees do you meane? wee Presbyterians, or wee Independents? for the latter, it is the fault of your pastour, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish him; you are grown to such a passe, the most of you, that you will never come to heare any, whom you think but Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian: what? would you have us speak so loud, that you should heare in your chimny corners? are you at church, and do you not heare? The more shame for you for sleeping; other men can heare that <hi>Discipline and Vniformity</hi> are, first very seldom preacht for, not so often as they should be: because there be other things, which stand in neerer relation to salvation; when did Master <hi>Thornbeck,</hi> or Master <hi>Carter</hi> preach a Sermon fully and abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely about discipline? If a Schismatick, or an heritick lies in their way (I trow) you will give them leave to kick them out, if you will not, they will take it.</p>
            <p>Secondly: when at all preach'd for very necessarily, when the City is infected with a thing they call a Church of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, that is to say, <hi>Brownists, Anabaptists,</hi> and <hi>Antinomians:</hi> they do not much delight in administring such Physick, but Antidotes are seasonable in time of infection: tis time to give pills when the body is infected, let them please, or not please: they are wholesome.</p>
            <p>I appeale to the right worshipfull and worthy Major, the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen</hi> and <hi>Common Councill.</hi> and all the Citizens of <hi>Norwich,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113813:13"/> the members of that faction) Is Mr. <hi>Thornbecks,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> constant preaching, <hi>for Discipline and Ʋniformitie? do they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preach for faith or repentance? &amp;c.</hi> Nay, is not ten Sermons, for one, of this Subject? If they bee; see what conscience this Tribe makes of lying and defaming: and take heed of their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Have ye nothing preached <hi>but the formes and shells of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Doe you know what Religion is? Sir, your tongue cannot defame these Ministers. Nay if at any time Mr. <hi>T.</hi> speakes any thing against Sectaries, doth not he use to distinguish betwixt those <hi>that are meerly misled,</hi> &amp; those <hi>that wilfully trouble the Church?</hi> Doth not he pity the first, and reprove and condemn the latter? you that are of that tribe, and are godly, judge your selves; doth he speake truth or no? Sure this is a rotten Gangren'd member. Is this Lyer a visible Saint amongst you?</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Thirdly from their unwillingnesse to let the Remonstrance be read in the Court of Majoralty, and after refusing to let the Town-Clarke read it, but would read it themselves: he observes very wittily the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull pertinacious conceitednesse these men have of their own worth; and their low, mean, &amp; unworthy opinion they have of all other men: had they not had high thoughts of themselves, they would have been willing, not only to let them have the hearing of it, but also have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired their advice, counsell, and help in the matter it selfe, and whole disposition and frame thereof: had they not very low and meane thoughts of that Court, it could not so much as enter into their hearts once to imagine, that ever they would entertaine such a motion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an utter disdaining thereof: That men could be imagined, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the chiefe Magistrates of that worthy Citie, to bee at such a vast distance from the wits and judgements of Rationall men, as to be led like a company of blinde buzzards into such dangerous transactions as there are, and that without so much as once examining and scanning the thing it selfe, and the tendency thereof. Surely had they not thought they had been a company of Idiots, made up into a Corporation, they would never have made such an unreasonable motion. But, you see, Mr. <hi>Thornbecke</hi> and the rest of your brethren! that Lay-men have their eyes in their heads. And doubtlesse hereafter they will examine your Doctrine before they will make application thereof:</q>
               <hi>well done good brother, but basely spoke.</hi> I must divide this, and search the fly-blown joynts severally.</p>
            <p>In this speech take notice:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113813:14"/>1. Of a large lye insinuated. That these reverend men were such conceited men: they thought Mr. Town-Clerke could not read it; and that they would scarce let the Court heare it, but at no hand take advice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An unmannerly slander suggested. Mark his words, men that <hi>would but entertaine a motion to heare a Remonstrance, to bee at such a vast distance from the wits and judgments of rationall men, as to be led like a company of blinde buzzards. Bona Verba quaeso:</hi> you are too sawcy Sir, &amp;c. <hi>had not they thought they had beene a company of Idiots, &amp;c.</hi> they <hi>would not have made, &amp;c.</hi> As much as to say, thats our judgment of them, &amp;c. Sure that Court will take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it. But they know you and your tongue.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An application: nothing to the purpose:</p>
            <p>To answer a little. It was not out of a pertinacious concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednesse the men had of their own worth, that they first could have beene content indeed that their Remonstrance should not have been read at that time. Secondly, when it was desired, they desired it to be read by one of themselves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because they would take a little more advice upon it, and present it perfect to the whole Court, June 19. at the Common Councell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because it it was written in a rude draught blotted, and enterlined, and not fit to be read by any, but he that writ it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Because Mr. Town-Clerkes Wife they knew was one of that Tribe: and though they durst trust him with it: they knew not how far the friend in his bosome might prevaile with him, and they were loath to trust one of their Adversaries with their weapon. But being desired by the Major, Master <hi>Carter</hi> read it, at that time, this was a wonderfull pertinacious conceitednesse, was it not? It being read, the Court desired it should be left with them for a day. The Ministers accordingly left it with the Major: was this such a blind leading of the Magistrates (Brother) that the Magistrates must be <hi>Idiots, blinde buzzards,</hi> to entertaine the motion. Was here no <hi>hearing, reading, debating, advising about it?</hi> If you would but learne to shame the Divell by speaking trueth once, we would have hopes of you: In conclusion, at night they repaired to the Court. The Major told them what they found fault with: which was something about Treasons, which they satisfied them, there was a statute in force against. Accordingly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113813:14"/> they blotted it cleare out. They likewise presented the Ministers there with a paper of what they found fault with, which was all presently amended: and they desired the Court; <hi>If they saw any thing in it (not in their judgements) fit to passe, or any thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective fit to be inserted: they would propound it; it should be taken from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r added to it. Or if the Court pleased to appoint a Committee to consult with them about any thing in it, or any thing to be added to it, it should be yeelded to.</hi> The Court was satisfied. Was not this faire dealing? What need they use now, Sir, to tell Mr. <hi>Thornbecke</hi> and Mr. <hi>Carter,</hi> Lay-men <hi>had eyes in their heads?</hi> We know it Sir, and can see your knavish and ungodly dealing with them, slandering Magistrates, Ministers, all the godly Ministers of a Citie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>But lastly, from the same particular, whether wee will or no, he will observe the <hi>Jesuiticall practises, and undermining principles of these kinde of men:</hi> manners (good Sir) Jesuites, underminers? well: you can talk of theirs: but wee shall prove yours to your face anon. Well: <hi>What are these Jesuites undermining principles? why would they not</hi> (they did Sir) <hi>suffer men to read, and observe, and debate that thing which they would have passe for their own act?</hi> All this was suffered, if you would be content with reason, Sir. Well he guesseth the reason, his quick nose hath sented it. <hi>They were conscious that too much care and inspection would prevent their designe: the light of reason, and the darkenesse of Contrivance would not consist together.</hi> Well guess't (Brother!) No Sir, they were afraid to leave it in your hands, lest you should have corrupted their writings, perverted their meanings: if you could raise such a competent sum of falshoods with but once hearing of it; What would you have done with writing of it out, especially when it was not to be printed. We knew your faculty at that trade too well: and if it had been left with the Aldermen, we know, though none were members, yet some stood in some relation to you. Thus you have the true account of the proceedings that day, and the true reason why they refused to leave the Copy. It is not so pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall possibly as might be expected. I was not so nice in that, because I am confident those reverend men will vindicate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves shortly. He goes on still.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">An Assembly or Common-counsell being called, <hi>June 19. 1646.</hi> the said Ministers came with their Petition or Remonstrance,</q>
               <hi>but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113813:15"/> would not endure any Copy thereof or Notes to be taken.</hi> All this is true, and scarce another whole sentence in the Libel.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>He goes on commenting. <q rend="margQuotes">It is most cleare <hi>(in your eye, Sir)</hi> that this was intended as a meere snare or trap to catch the Citie:</q> (where was it set (Sir?) what was it baited with?) more befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Mountebancks then Ministers, that so the people may be engaged in before they were aware of it.</hi> Let the (Reader) judge the truth of this from what went before; he goes on prating as if his tongue were oyled, and his braines crackt, and he fitter to goe to <hi>Bedlam</hi> then to bee honoured with a confutation (how meane soever.) But to his story.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">The result of that meeting was, that the Assembly desired a weekes time to consider of it, and a Copy thereof to be left in their hands: both which the Ministers refusing to yield unto; nothing was done.</q> The truth is this.<note place="margin">Ʋid suprà</note> The Common-councell meeting, it was presented &amp; left with them, they all faithfully promising that no Notes of it should be taken for the reason above, though we must put them in minde by the way (to demonstrate their faithfulnesse to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) that Mr. <hi>Ashwell,</hi> one at whose house their tribe meetes notwithstanding his faithfull engagement amongst the rest, yet was found taking of Notes, which the Common-councell was much incenst with, alledging it was a dishonour to their Court, and he no honest man that should offer it. Their Speaker took his paper away in the Court, and would have rent it, had he not pleaded it was the backside of a Letter: whereupon they blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out what he had written, restored him his paper. But in conclusion, the Common-councell being informed by the Citie-Councell then present, of some inconveniences might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued, for the manner of presenting, not the matter of the thing; declared their minds to the Ministers, and they departed satisfied of the fidelity of that Court, and desire to oppose all Faction.</p>
            <p>For the few lines concerning Mr. <hi>Carters</hi> allegation, I shall leave them to Mr. <hi>Carter</hi> to answer, who I am confident wil take up the glove: only let me tell you, Mr. <hi>Carter</hi> is not such an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of Malignants, more then of Independents: for the <hi>naile strucke through</hi> Sisera's <hi>Temples,</hi> and the dead Remonstrance, the Reader hath the true story.</p>
            <p>Our Libeller now goes on to pick out something out of Mr. <hi>Ashwells</hi> notes: and so far <hi>as his memory could carry away,</hi> or his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113813:15"/> invention devise, <hi>they are these that follow.</hi> But before they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low he tells you, <hi>pure policy hath buried the</hi> Remonstrance <hi>in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity;</hi> good reason Sir! the Ministers in the City have been tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced enough, with the ends you have got. His text is now cleared from lying, for it is no more then memory could carry away, and his memory is like a snow-bal, it licks up, as it goeth.</p>
            <p>But first, <q rend="margQuotes">That no satisfaction was yet given to the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>-Remonstrance.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now he spends a meditation or two upon it, gnawes once or twice on this bone, <hi>Hee sees that London Remonstrance: through the skill and diligence of the busy Ministers,</hi> (speak no more than you know Sir) <hi>proves generative, and hath begotten a Norwich-Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance.</hi> And is it not good for Brethren to dwell together in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? But Sir. you are mistaken, London Remonstrance was a mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine Remonstrance: Iudicious discreet men that had a hand in it. They are your Female Petitions of the Independents that are the engenderers; such as are filled with maids and girles hands, But you <hi>say Abortion hath bin its doome:</hi> 'Tis false, Sir, they were brought all forth, as well as your independent petition Annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your libell: But we will prove that a Bastard anon, it was begott in a Corner: though an Attourney was the father of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly: he would know, whether wee suppose that the Parliament of England had their dependence, strength, hope, and confidence, so in the London Remonstrance, as that whatsoever they should require, though it should bee Iohn Baptists head, to the prejudice, yea the danger of half,</hi> yea of the whole Kingdome; <hi>it must bee granted.</hi> Here he insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth, that London Remonstrance was a very prejudiciall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the lord major, <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Common Counsell</hi> of the City of London, are men of so little Religion that they would aske <hi>Iohn Baptists</hi> head; what would undoe the Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Sir. wee doe not suppose that the Parliament of England, hath any such <hi>Dependence, strength or hope in the City of London.</hi> Nor doe wee desire the great court of the Kingdome, should be tyed up to such necessity: or acted by such Principles. But when the body of the whole City of London, whose purses have been the nerves and sinnues of our defensive warres, whose bodies have been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly offered up to death; out of a meer principle of obedience
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113813:16"/> to the Parliament, and to make a Bulwark for them: I say, when these joyntly remonstrate their grievances, and petition Redresse, and their petition tends to the peace of the State, and vnity of the Church; wee cannot but lissen after the answer, and beleeve, it will in time bee Satisfactory.</p>
            <p>For what followeth of certaine men, of Master <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becks, and</hi> Master <hi>Carters tribe: being moved by the deceitfull compasse of carnall interest: and being acted and moved up and downe, according to the motions of their primum-mobile, Worldly Preferment and popular concurrence, Submitting your selves to the precepts of men: to Surplice, Tippets, High-Altar, Lyturgies, Homilies, Cannons, Injunctions, if the Bishops preach for them, and glory in them: and as the times wheele a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout againe; they can throw them all by, and bee as zealous against them as ever you were for them.</hi> I suppose you have not brazen-face e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to accuse Master <hi>Carter:</hi> yet you put it in a Dialect, like the Devills Oracle, no one knowes to construe it: "<hi>For men of your tribe,</hi> Master <hi>Thornbeck,</hi> Master <hi>Carter, and the rest of you to be steered, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is no matter, your tongue is not worth regarding, if you do: only, if you do; it was no policy to send your bookes into <hi>Norwich,</hi> where the whole City can give you the lye; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, his leaving of his Living at St. <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Norwich</hi> for 2. years together, Indeed he did not run over into <hi>Holland</hi> and gather a Church: It would have troubled his Spirit perhaps, to have left his sinking Kingdome, much more to have spent his time in Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a foundation, for future disturbances of the Church, he was not at the Christning of that (Infant then) Independency.</p>
            <p>Indeed, there was of your (friends) that would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, (yet even they conformed to a Surplesse &amp;c.) but shewed themselves men of conscience in, denying those things which they durst not doe, as well as in doing what they might do, with (as they thought) a safe concience, But there was a little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Master <hi>Carters</hi> going, and theirs; when they did, Master <hi>Carter</hi> and his wife going when they had no maintenance assured, nor any place where they were confident, they might lay down their head: Tis one thing for conscience sake, thus to go and throw themselves upon a frowning Providence, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing to go assured of 20 pounds <hi>per annum</hi> from one Gentlewoman, and to a Living of six or sevenscore pounds <hi>per
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113813:16"/> annum,</hi> paid clearly, twice so good as that in <hi>Norwich;</hi> and but two dayes journey.</p>
            <p>And I hope you have more modesty then to accuse Mr. <hi>Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke</hi> of those tricks: what ever you say.<note place="margin">☜</note> If the Reader doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, he may enquire at <hi>Bumstead</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> where was his then residence, whether he was not by the Bishops excomunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for not conforming to their Injunctions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, you tell us, if we will forbeare a little, there will be satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction sufficient to the joy of the Kingdome, From the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>concerning</hi> London<hi>-Remonstrance:</hi> we hope so too. <hi>And though it hath been the joy and gladnesse, hope and confidence, waters of life to the fainting hearts: yea as butter and honey, marrow &amp; fatnesse in the mouths of Malignants.</hi> Malignants Sir? whom doe you call Malignants? what! the House of Peers that have their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it? and all our <hi>Brethren of</hi> Scotland, and the <hi>godly and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Ministers of the Kingdome?</hi> what! all Malignants (Brother?) who is bitter now? what those thousands Orthodox Protestants in the Kingdome, whose hearts were with the Remonstrants in those things that concerned the Kingdome; all Malignants? sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Author, was brought up in a dung-hill by his foule mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet that he hopes the Parliaments answer will be as gall &amp; worm-wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and gravell in their bellies, quashing their spirits, and dashing their hopes: yea and satisfaction in abundance to the true-hearted and well-affected in the Kingdome.</hi> We know what you would have, wee would but only understand whom you meane by the well-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted party in the Kingdome. But to put you partly out of doubt. The <hi>Honourable House of Peers</hi> have given in their part of satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. All that is expected is the answer of the <hi>Honourable House of Commons.</hi> From whom without question, the Remonstrants do not doubt of satisfaction. But this is to make the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve what great friends you have Above: how great a stroake in the <hi>House,</hi> &amp;c. That this single man can assure such an answer, and knowes the heart of the house what will be the major Vote when it comes to be debated!</p>
            <p>A second particle of the Remonstrance complained of, is, <q rend="margQuotes">That the Declaration of the <hi>17.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> last past, was a grieving of the hearts of Gods people, and taking off the hearts of the Parliaments best friends.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113813:17"/>
            <p>For the truth of the Clause, I say nothing: who so enquires what entertainment it found in all places where were no Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, will ghesse whither the clause be true or false.</p>
            <p>For the Relative truth of it, whether it was in the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance or no I know not: and in this case shall desire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to wait for the Defendents Vindication of themselves, and let no man condemn them <hi>before he hath heard them speak. Si satis sit accusari nullus erit innocens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I take notice of your note that Mr. <hi>Thornbeck</hi> and Mr. <hi>Carter</hi> are very carefull <hi>that Gods people have not their hearts grieved:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>you hope they are against that State-troubling Principle, drunk in by many of their Tribe, </hi>viz.<hi> the compelling of men against their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences to Ʋniformity in Church-government, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Hold there, Sir, you snap fearfully: stay while the bone is thrown you. These men are tender of the griefe of Gods people: but it doth not follow therefore that they are <hi>against compelling of men against their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences to Ʋniformitie in Church-government.</hi> There is a difference Sir betwixt <hi>Scandalum datum &amp; inventum,</hi> or <hi>acceptum,</hi> a scandall or a griefe given: and just this they are tender of, and a scandall or a grief taken or invented, and unjust. The mother is tender of making the child cry without a cause but if it will fit pouting in a corner it knows not for what cause it selfe, but meerly because it will have its will, or the whole house shall be troubled with it; then she whips it. There is again another difference betwixt compelling a conscience which cannot be compel'd, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a practise and another difference betwixt <hi>compelling a man to practise this, or else make them doe it</hi> as <hi>Antiochus</hi> made the good Jewes to eate Swines flesh, and the Papists would have made the Protestants turne: or the Turks will make the Christians be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised will they nill they, and <hi>enjoyning them if they stay in the Kingdome to doe it:</hi> if they cannot, they shall neither have bodies punished, nor States confiscated, but they may goe where they may have a toleration. The first they loath. And desire not the second till necessity call for it. <hi>Melius pereat Ʋnus quàm unitas.</hi> They are tender of any thing that is a just griefe to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and are against any compulsion of conscience (which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be compeld) or of practice so far as to persecute with fire &amp; faggot, or death, or any mulct or confiscation unlesse by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of injunctions of lawful authority, they after shall incurre such a censure.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:113813:17"/>
            <p>For what else is in your notes upon that text, I leave it to themselves to answer.</p>
            <p>The third thing he complaines of, which should have beene Remonstrated and desired, is;</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>That Church Governement might be setled according to our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Reader! do'st not wonder where this fellow left his modesty when hee complained against this part of the Remonstrance? Marke with how much modesty and pious zeale this Petition is mixed, that a man would admire what this black-mouth'd Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus can carpe at.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Church Governement might be setled.</hi> And is it not the panting of all that are godly in the Nation? O, we are undone for want of Governmen; what hearts that are honest bleede not to see Gods people seduced? No Sacraments scarce administred: Anabaptists dipping even to death: Coblers Preaching: every venemous tongue railing against all Authority, yea, and all that is called God too almost: Every poysonous pen shewing it selfe against Gods people, truth, Ordinances, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What man, that hath the heart of a man, hath not a bleeding heart for these distractions? &amp; a soul, that pants not for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of the Church? especially that these Ministers. Who should complaine for want of an hedge: but the husbandman? especially the Ministers of <hi>Norwich</hi> that are sensible of the want by the daily infection of divers, who though they be but of the inferior sort of women, &amp;c. yet have equally immortall soules. O, but what Governement would these Ministers have? What! Episcopacy againe? or some Government model'd out by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. No, onely the Governement that is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to our Covenant;</hi> The duty of the Parliament shall bound these Remonstrants desires. We have lift up our hands to the most high God. O that we would not goe back. Is this such a harsh Petition? <hi>We humbly beseech you that are our noble Senators, to set up a Governement in our Church, pittying the rending of our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and the dividing of your people, and the infecting of our flocks: Settle us such a Governement as we have sworne to the most high God to stablish, that no guilt of perjury ly upon any of our souls. As we have sworn so let us performe.</hi> Is this such a designe? O, but he knowes, If the Sun shines, the Owles must to their Ivies. This faction is that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113813:18"/> that that is onely rich in the ruines of the Church and prospers in the desolations of Sion. Church Governement is this broods greatest grievance, <hi>his craft is done if that once bee setled.</hi> Now he puffs and speakes Bulls, any thing in his note.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What hinders you that you doe not endeavour to settle it according to your Covenant?</hi> (you Sir, and your faction.) <hi>Nay why doe you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, preach against, and trouble those that do settle Church Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to their Covenant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> He that runs may reade this, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But Sir, how shall wee settle it? Have the Presbyters (any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where but in <hi>London,</hi> and that only for the Classes there) power to ordaine according to the Ordinance, or any power to Elect Elders? Is the Presbyterie confirmed according to the names sent up to the Parliament? if not, where's the power? and who preaches against those that doe settle it according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? I hope you doe not thinke Independency is a Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Let the name speake; <hi>But the mouth of those that speake lies shall be stopt,</hi> 63. <hi>Psal.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Another head is, <hi>That children are left unbaptized. That he sayes is the fault of the Parents, not of the Parliament, we would have them, hee sayes, leave the businesse of the Kingdome, and Baptize our Children, why doe we trouble them about it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not a just complaint that children are left unbaptized al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in all parts of the Kingdome? partly because there is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury of Ministers; partly because Independents have got the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, &amp; they will baptize none but their owne members breede; partly because wee have no penall Law against those that shall wilfully neglect Gods ordinance, nor those that shall renounce their Christianity, and be redipped againe, yea and that in Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous manner. One in <hi>Essex</hi> (if I mistate not) being so Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and the wretch that did it, bid him <hi>Receive the Holy Ghost,</hi> and within two dayes the new convert runns stark mad; a just example of Gods Vengeance. Is it not a piteous thing that in <hi>Sudbury,</hi> a Corporation-towne in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> consisting of three great Parishes, and now two Ministers there, and none Baptizeth, but those that will bring the children to the Ordinance must get a Minister out of the places adjacent? Those that will wrong their children so as not to have them Baptized, may, we doe not desire <hi>the Parliament to Baptize them Sir, nor dare the Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to doe it.</hi> It is the impudence of your Laity to put their hands
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113813:18"/> into such sacred services, but wee could wish some penall Law were against Independents, Anabaptists, and some Governement setled; that those that preach might Baptize <hi>as well the Body as private members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Particle he carpes at is,</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>That there were no Church-officers to look to the poore.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This your memory failed in. It was, that there were no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Officers,</hi> viz. <hi>Deacons,</hi> (as in the Apostolicall Institution) <hi>to look to the poore. The law of Nature, and the law of the Land tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to look to the poore, and it seemes wee are but poore Preachers, that we have taught the people no better.</hi> That the poore are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. Speak sence (Sir) are you sure we teach not our people to look to the poore; is it our fault for want of preaching, or theirs for want of practising what we preach? But are not the poore neglected amongst the Independents, and in Norwitch too? Doth there none complaine, that you promised, when they were admitted into your Society, more charity then ever you performed? <hi>Turpe est doctori, &amp;c.</hi> Sir, mend at home.</p>
            <p>Another particular.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">That there were thirty six Parishes in Norwich, and twenty six without Ministers.</q> He is angry that this is spoken of; the Fox might have lyen here, and killed many a Lambe, and none ever took notice of it: the Sheep are without a Shepheard: But is not this piteous? But, as if he were <hi>the Speaker of both Houses, he tells Mastr</hi> Thornebeck, <hi>hee needs not complaine of that, hee may doe well to procure</hi> 26. <hi>Ministers more.</hi> Yes Sir, and who shall procure maintenance? and who shall ordaine them to their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places? The <hi>Parliament hath given full power and authority;</hi> for what Sir, to leavy meanes for them? or to ordaine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors for each Congregation? or to chuse Elders? In what Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance is this power given to any, but the City of <hi>London?</hi> Speake Sir, to those that know not: these truth will not goe off hand else. He sayes, <hi>in the meane while wee might doe well to entertain our neighbours into our Congregations.</hi> Whom do ye mean, our neighbour Independents? which of you have been denyed? (provided that you would take a Pastorall charge.) Indeed, when motion was made for a call of Master <hi>Bridges</hi> to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; some of the discreet Magistrates denyed their hands, except hee would take a Pastorall charge. But if yee will onely bee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113813:19"/> journey-men, wee have nothing to doe with you. Who hires a a Wolfe for his Shepheard? he tells Master <hi>Thornbeck</hi> he might doe some good, <hi>by his preaching, upon his Neighbour-Malignants.</hi> Which of them, Sir? <hi>those that throng so much after you?</hi> Had not some Tinker plated this Sectaries face, hee would have blushed. This man, whom he accuseth (Master Thornebeck) is the shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest and severest man against Malignants, (as all that know him can testifie) in all the Association almost; yet he insinuates, that he is the onely man that Malignants love and throng too. Enquire at <hi>Rumford</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> and <hi>Kelved</hi> on <hi>Esterford,</hi> and <hi>Bures</hi> St. <hi>Mary</hi> in Suffolke, the places of his residence, and at <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich:</hi> but this is one of the <hi>new truths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another particular he is angry with, is, that they should joyne with the <hi>Londoners</hi> in Petitioning.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">That such as separate from the Church of <hi>England</hi> might not have any place in the Church, Common-wealth, or Army.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis false (Sir) your memory failed you, it was, <hi>any place of trust.</hi> Well, now he chides fearefully: he tells us, <hi>When satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is given to the London Remonstrants, then we shall know the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments pleasures in that point.</hi> Till then we wait in hope. In the meane time he bids us follow our studies, (and you your shop-board, and leave lying) <hi>and learne your selves</hi> (and you some manners, Sir) and teach <hi>your people better manners,</hi> and you more wit, Sir,) <hi>then to order the Parliament whom to trust in the publike af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the kingdome;</hi> we only desire, &amp; Remonstrate our desires.</p>
            <p>For the next: It is answered by the Parliament; I shall passe it over. It only Remonstrated how desirous we were of an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable peace, if it might have been obtained.</p>
            <p>For the next, <hi>That Comissioners were never knowne in the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall government.</hi> This likewise is answered: We rest for that.</p>
            <p>But for the last.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">That Traitors to the King were not executed.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>This is a falshood <hi>per totum:</hi> No such clause was in the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance presented <hi>June</hi> 19. nor was there ever a syllable of Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in it. Let the foole runne his length here, it nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes us. Well, now he drawes towards a conclusion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There</hi> (some of these, and some part of them) <hi>were some of the heads of the said Remonstrance presented by the fore-said Ministers, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis true in part. And <hi>many of the well-affected</hi> Malignants, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113813:19"/> Antinomians, Anabaptists, Men, Women, and Children, <hi>having intelligence thereof:</hi> it was not carryed so secretly, but you might have <hi>applyed your selves, with all expedition, to the framing a Petition, to present to the Parliament.</hi> Very discreetly done, Sir, <hi>to present to the Parliament, to shew their respect to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> Speak the whole truth, Brother, was that all? <hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Remonstrance,</hi> how should that hinder you? which (<hi>if it had passed the Vote of the Common-Councell,</hi> to present to the Parliament) <hi>they would have brought up to the Parliament.</hi> It would have been wisely done, who would have hindred? No question the Parliament desires to know the Kingdomes grievances. Your Brethren of <hi>London</hi> had done the like before, and the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable House of Commons gave them thanks, Sir. But you would not have had the whole <hi>thousand hands</hi> that you boast of all gone up in person then, would yee? how many must have gone in the Nurses Armes then? and how many must you have been bound for to have returned safely to Gaole then? And how many Malignants must have gone, that durst as well take a Lion by the tooth, as look upon a Parliament-House? And how many poore lob-led Innocents, that knew not what they did! But (Reader) I will lay open these juglers to you. I shall shew you how they got their thousand hands to this Petition, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Petition before: and thou shalt see what a generation of well-affected, these Brethren a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>These Gentlemen hearing of this Remonstrance, which they judged prejudiciall to their cause; thought it was time to <hi>get up, and be doing.</hi> Whereupon Master <hi>H. K.</hi> &amp; Master <hi>G.B.</hi> (who should be Doctor, if he would keep his Act) goe and draw this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Petition annexed, and brought it to the Committe of <hi>Accompts</hi> there: one or two subscribed it, the rest refusing. Presently it was disperst about the Countrey in the name of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte, which the poore people had thought had been the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte of the County. This was done secretly, till it was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by a Gentleman at <hi>Windham,</hi> and brought to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte of the County, who all disclaimed it: and these two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, (being Committees) being challenged for abusing the whole Committee, to send out Petitions in their names; They wound off with an evasion, that they intended the Committee of Accompts, at which one Gentleman that was there, told
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113813:20"/> them hee was of that Committe, and no such thing past that Board. In conclusion, these two were the men. See now, where are the Jesuiticall practises? who is the Jesuite now, Brother?)</p>
            <p n="1">1. They send it to people that are in the simplicity of their hearts led away, and set their hands to they know not what; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they hear it comes from good men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They send it in the Committees name, by whom all would judge that heare. They would have it understood the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees for the County. But thirdly, when their Plot is discovered.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Then (by their Jesuiticall reservation, they escape (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) they meant the Committee of Accompts. Why did not they speak plaine then?</p>
            <p>In the meane while, a Letter is written to <hi>Hingham</hi> in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk, where grave, and godly Master <hi>Peck</hi> is Minister: If I mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not, it was writ to the High Constable; the matter was, to perswade him, to get hands to the Petition, and they shoul doe an <hi>Acceptable service to that Board.</hi> I had thought to have given the Reader an exact coppy of their Letter, <hi>verbatim;</hi> but it could not be gotten so suddenly as to insert in this Pamphlet: for I was was willing to pursue the Thief with an <hi>Hue-and-Cry,</hi> before he was entertained, and any made accessary to his Villany. You shall have it in my next, with all particulars.</p>
            <p>In the meane while, another is sent towards <hi>Soffam,</hi> there was a drunken meeting, and (if I remember right) a wrestling after, with one of these Emissaries. When they had all drunke suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, to banish both their wit &amp; reason, stammered out this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition; and for a jugge of Beere might five hundred hands be got at that time. Every one uttered his minde freely: and from that vomiting, very like, came a great part of their hands. (I may mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, through information; but if I doe, I will amend it in the next.)</p>
            <p>Then consider, who they sent to for hands: the most despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Malignants in Norfolk, and persecutors of all goodnesse. Witnesse, the first hand which was subscribed to one Coppy of your Petition, which was a Ministers, who is noted for a desperate Malignant. And Sr. <hi>Ch. A.</hi> the onely Knight I know you can bragge of; and this <hi>well-affected man</hi> was sequestred, and newly come home from Newarke; 'tis possible something might be promised him from these men too; or at least hee might bee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113813:20"/> feared by them. Delinquents, Malignants, Drunkards, Swearers, all <hi>well-affected?</hi> others seduced deceived At last with this scraping, and <hi>omnium gatherum,</hi> they come to the Court of Major and Aldermen; they with a great deale of Indignation, and <hi>Odium,</hi> threw it out. Then they brought it to the Committee for the County. In the Interim, some discreet and well-affected Gentlemen, having notice of these under-board practices, drew another Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which owned the Covenant and Presbyteriall government modestly. To which Petition, the Major, and well affected Aldermen, subscribed. A Coppy whereof, was sent to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the County, and well-affected people, <hi>(not to Delinquents, Sir, nor Newarkers.)</hi> The subscription was deferred, by some of the Knights, and Gentlemens appoyntment, till there were a generall meeting of the whole Committee of the County, which was to be about a fortnight after. In the meane time, they had the Petition returned, with some things altered and some thing added; with a desire that it might be prepared against the meeting. Two, or three were appointed for that purpose: but upon second thoughts (hints being given out by the Independents, that if this Petition might be laid down, they would lay downe theirs) and regarding the Juncture of time, being when the house was sending away the Propositions, it was concluded, to proceed no further for the present, in that, or any other, Petition. But we thought, lesse could not stand with good manners, then at the day when the Committee met, who had pleased, in the generall, to owne our Petition; then to go up, and, tendring our ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, thanke them; and declare our latter resolutions; and, as we thought (for the present) more expedient thoughts: Cōming thither, (beyond expectation) they met with Mr. <hi>H. K</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>G. B.</hi> in an out-room, where, after some conference about both the Petition, a motion was made, that the controversie should be referred to the Committe then met, if they would be pleased to trouble themselves with it. Who, though their occasions were great at present, gave the gentlemen audience: and after some debate, the major part advised us, that both Petitions should be laid aside for the present, in respect of the weighty affaires the Parl. had then in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. The Ministers, and well affected, presently condescended; but Mr. <hi>H. K</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>G. B</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing desired to do the same, answered, (according to <hi>Lilbourns</hi> president) <hi>They were free born subjects,</hi> Whereupon the Committee shewed great dislike of their carriage. And the Ministers finding such candid, and courteous, carriage from the gentlemen of the Committee, did engage themselves, not to set any Petition on foot, before they had first acquainted the said Cōmittee with it, and imparted it to them, (provided, that the other party of Independents, Malignants, &amp;c. should do the same. Their answer was still, <hi>They were free borne Subjects.</hi> But the Mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sters engaged themselves, that they would stand to what they had promised. And at their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Mr. <hi>Thornbeck</hi> made this motion to the Board: That in case these Sectaries should (all this notwithstanding) proceed in theirs, the Committee would be pleased to discountenance and suppresse them: Which then one of them promised he would doe; and so he thought the rest would. None gain-sayed it. The Committee thanked the Ministers for their honest and plaine dealing; and as much checked the other: The Ministers taking their leave, Mr. <hi>Carter</hi> made this motion; That that Worshipfull Board, would be pleased to take especiall notice (as no question they did) of eithers carryage and iudge accordingly.</p>
            <p>Thus (Reader) thou hast the perfect story Now (brother) who was the Jugler? who the <hi>Jesuite?</hi> who the <hi>State-disturbers?</hi> who the <hi>pertinacious conceited men?</hi> Is this true now, thinke you, that you are meer <hi>passive creatures, and act nothing?</hi> that dare send out Petitions in the name of the Committee, without their knowledg, and controul the whole Committee? Are you the onely free born subiects of the kingdom? Is it your Birth-right to petition, &amp; not ours? Is it a state-disturbance for us to petition, &amp; not for you too? remember what you writ <hi>p.</hi> 2. Is it none for you, though the whole Committee for the county be against you? Alas, you are <hi>holy, harmles, peaceable</hi> (speak truth Sir) creatures, <hi>useful to the publike:</hi> for what? to set it on fire? But I must take notice of the Petition, p. 16. being you have printed Either our coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sell,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113813:21"/> or yours told us it was a breach of priviledge of Parliament, &amp; high forfeiture, to print any thing that was directed to the Parliament, whether Petition or Remonstrance, &amp;c before i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had been presented to the House.</p>
            <p>But these are the priviledged men, that can break no priviledges, forfeit no estate: but why do you say, The <hi>Humble Petition of the Knights, &amp;c.</hi> What Knight? Sir, except Sir <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Atto,</hi> just let out of <hi>Newarke. Ge tlemen?</hi> which of them, Sir; did not the whole board declare against you? <hi>Free-holders;</hi> how many of them Sir? and Inhabitants <hi>of the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty of</hi> Norfolke What Inhabitants? Men, women, the boyes, girles, simple people that knew nothing, but were Tenants, or in some relation to you? <hi>And the City of Norwich.</hi> What more still? why then did the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or and Aldermen, and that representative Citie cast it out? it should have run thus. The Petition of the <hi>Independents, Delinquents, Malignants, Anabaptists, Antinomia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Gallioes,</hi> and 2 or 3 honester men of the County of Norfolke, and County and City of Norwich. For the Petition it selfe, let the Parliament judg it. They have appealed thither, thither let them goe. Here was the Rise, Progresse, and Ruine of it.</p>
            <p>Nor was this their first jugling with petitioning. Once before they sent out a dangerous Petition, which (if I mistake not) was, for an intolerable Toleration. This was likewise sent out from the same hands in the name of the Committeee for the County of Norfolke: the manner was to have Copies of it drawn, and (as I am informed) when any of the Country-men came about any County-bus ness, he was by one or two of them calld aside, and a copy given to them to get hands to, as a Petition from the Committee. This was likewise discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a discreet Gentleman at <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndham,</hi> and taken from Captaine <hi>B</hi> and this Gentleman brought it to one of the Committee, who the next day carried it to the Committee: who all disclaimed it, except those two which were the Authors of it, and resented the matter of so high concernment, and so scandalous, that some of the Gentlemen present thought it fit they should be censured for that abuse of the Country-Gentlemen, and lesse-understanding peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But in conclusion they were well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hidden for it, and the matter buried.</p>
            <p>Reader, <hi>Ex ungue leonem.</hi> Construe these men as you find them, and trust them according to their trustinesse. I had thought to have added here a full relation of their rise, progresse, number, and carriage in this Citie. And to have answered the latter part of the Booke falsly stiled <hi>Vox Populi.</hi> But, it would for the present take up too much time, and I am willing to pursue the <hi>Fox</hi> while the sent is hot. I am confident some of the Ministers too will take them to task, and an answer for themselves. But if not, I shall in convenient time delineate them, and give thee a perfect draught, and stop the mouth of <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> and present thee with their cry against that Faction, and their undermining dealings amongst us. But let mee acquaint thee what entertainment this scurrilous pamphlet found in this Citie. Threescore and odde of them were sent down to Mr. <hi>I. T.</hi> (they say) a chiefe Independent in this City: which being discovered to the Right Worshipfull the Major of the Citie: hee viewing the Book, altogether a libellous scandall, belying both the Magistracy and the Ministerie, and reviling all, and having no <hi>Imprimatur</hi> to it; sends one of his Officers and ceaseth upon the packet as unlicensed libellous printed untruths: for hee durst nor credit that piece of the Frontispiece <hi>Licensed and entred according to Order</hi> except he knew by whom) and tooke them to his Custody till he should find out who licensed them, who writ them, &amp; who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished them, that the Author might be proceeded against as a Libeller, &amp; if the book bee not licensed (as no rationall man can beleeve) we wil tell you the end of it hereafter. Till when, goood Reader farewell.</p>
            <p>For the latter part <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> it is wholly true for the matter. If one word were but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Title, &amp; it were <hi>Vox Populi Independentis:</hi> Who say <hi>Their tongues are their own &amp; they will speake,</hi> and must do so too, till God &amp; Authority stop their mouths. <hi>Quod faxit Deus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ja: Cranford,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date> Sept. 2. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>